Guide to the William Preston Few Records and Papers, 1814 - 1971 and undated (bulk 1911-1940) UA.03.55.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Subject Files
  - Few, William Preston
    - Speeches, Writings, and Lecture Notes, 1910-1940 and undated
      - Speeches, Writings, and Lecture Notes, undated (Box 115, Folder 1228-1235)
      - Dangers and Disadvantages of our System of Common School Education, n.d (Box 115, Folder 1236)
        Includes printed material.
      - Speeches, Writings, and Lecture Notes, undated (Box 116, Folder 1237-1244)
      - Speeches, Writings, and Lecture Notes, 1920-1939 and undated (Box 116, Folder 1245)
      - The Beginnings of an American University
        - In the Beginning (Box 116, Folder 1246-1247)
          Includes chapters on The Founding, The Law School, The Co-ordinate College for Women, The Medical School, Forestry, The Duke Undergraduates and their Colleges, Education and Religion, The Building, The Inaugural Address, Washington Duke, and The Launching of Duke University.
        - The Beginnings of an American University, 1932 and undated (Box 117, Folder 1248)
          Includes chapters on The Launching of Duke University, Contributions of the Duke Family to Education, Personal Statement, Undertakings of Duke University and the Spirit that Prompted Them, and An Old College and a New University.
        - An Old College and a New University (Box 117, Folder 1249)
        - In the Beginning (Box 117, Folder 1250)
        - Founding of the University (Box 117, Folder 1251)
        - Duke Divinity School (Box 117, Folder 1252)
        - The Graduate School (Box 117, Folder 1253)
        - The Law School (Box 117, Folder 1254)
        - The Medical School (Box 117, Folder 1255)
        - A North Carolina Medical School (Box 117, Folder 1256)
          The controversy of 1922 and 1923 as reported by the newspapers.
        - Colleges-- Coordinate and Engineering (Box 117, Folder 1257)
        - Forestry (Box 117, Folder 1258)
        - Trinity College (Box 117, Folder 1259)
        - Government and Administration (Box 117, Folder 1260)
        - Education and Religion (Box 117, Folder 1261)
        - Building (Box 117, Folder 1262)
        - Inaugural (Box 117, Folder 1263)
        - Washington Duke (Box 117, Folder 1264)
        - Appendix (Box 117, Folder 1265)
      - Shakespeare (Box 117, Folder 1266-1268)
        Includes manuscript on the writings of Shakespeare and their relation to modern life.
      - Writings for the Duke Chronicle (Box 117, Folder 1269)
  - Florida Southern College (Box 117, Folder 1270)
  - Freak Letters (Box 118, Folder 1271)
    Includes unusual letters received by Few while he was president.
  - Hart, Julian Deryl (Box 118, Folder 1272)
  - Hazen Foundation (Box 118, Folder 1273)
  - Institute on Southern Regional Development and the Social Sciences (Box 118, Folder 1274)
  - International Council of Religious Education (Box 118, Folder 1275)
  - Junaluska School of Religion (Box 118, Folder 1276)
  - Kilgo, John Carlisle (Box 118, Folder 1277)
  - Lake Junaluska Methodist Assembly, 1936-1940
    Includes copies of correspondence received by the Lake Junaluska Methodist Assembly staff, certificates of incorporation, correspondence with Few, printed matter, and other materials pertaining to the Assembly.
    - Lake Junaluska Methodist Assembly, 1936-1939 (Box 118, Folder 1278-1285)
    - Lake Junaluska Methodist Assembly, 1938-1940 (Box 119, Folder 1286-1287)
  - Lincoln Memorial University (Box 119, Folder 1288)
  - Masaryk, Thomas G. (Box 119, Folder 1289)
  - McDougall, William (Box 119, Folder 1290)
  - Medical College for North Carolina, 1922-1923 (Box 119, Folder 1291)
  - Methodist Board of Publication, 1923-1939 (Box 119, Folder 1292)
  - Methodist Episcopal Church, South, 1921-1938 and undated
    Includes material on the development of Christian education; correspondence about the organization and daily business of the district of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South; printed matter collected by Few about religious education; and Few's activities related to his membership on the Board of Education and the Board of Lay Activities. Much of the correspondence is addressed to Prof. F.S. Aldridge, District Lay Leader, and to Few, Conference Lay Leader. Printed material includes Stewardship Manual for the Methodist Episcopal Church, South; Handbook of the Wesley Brotherhood, 1924; and small pamphlets published by the Church.
    - Board of Education (Box 119, Folder 1293)
    - Christian Education Movement (Box 119, Folder 1294)
    - General Board of Christian Education (Box 119, Folder 1295-1296)
    - Correspondence (Box 120)
      - 1921-1925 (Box 120, Folder 1297)
      - 1925-1927 (Box 120, Folder 1298)
      - 1927-1930 (Box 120, Folder 1299)
    - Printed Material (Box 120, Folder 1300)
    - General Board of Lay Activities (Box 121, Folder 1301-1306)
    - Laymen's Missionary Movement (Box 121, Folder 1307)
    - Miscellaneous Methodist Church Material (Box 121, Folder 1308)
      Includes printed material about theological schools, the educational council of the Methodist Episcopal Church, the aldersgate commemoration; a manuscript on the History of New Hope Church; and correspondence.
    - North Carolina Conference (Box 121, Folder 1309)
    - Union with Northern Church (Box 122, Folder 1310-1317)
      In 1937, the members of the annual conferences of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South, voted on the Plan of Union for the unification of the Methodist Protestant Church, the Methodist Episcopal Church, and the Methodist Epicopal Church, South. The final vote was overwhelmingly in favor of the union, but there ensued a movement to block the union of these three Methodist groups. Included are correspondence, questionnaires, printed matter, and reports about this unification.
    - Western North Carolina Conference (Box 122, Folder 1318)
  - Morehead-Mebane Foundation (Box 122, Folder 1319)
  - Newbold, Nathan Carter (Box 122, Folder 1320)
  - New England Society, Charleston, S.C. (Box 122, Folder 1321)
  - North Carolina College Conference (Box 122, Folder 1322-1323)
  - North Carolina College Conference (Box 123, Folder 1324)
  - North Carolina Commission on Interracial Cooperation (Box 123, Folder 1326)
  - North Carolina Council of Churches (Box 123, Folder 1327)
  - Pastors' School (Box 123, Folder 1328)
  - Peabody (George) College for Teachers, Nashville, Tenn. (Box 123, Folder 1329)
  - Presidential Election, 1928 (Box 123, Folder 1330)
  - Printed Material (Box 123, Folder 1331)
  - Rosenwald Fund (Box 123, Folder 1332)
  - Seashore Summer School (Box 123, Folder 1333)
  - Southern Asso. of Colleges and Secondary Schools (Box 123, Folder 1334-1336)
  - Southern Conference (Box 123, Folder 1337)
  - Southern Council on International Relations (Box 123, Folder 1338)
  - Southern Education Foundation (Box 123, Folder 1339-1340)
  - Southern University Conference (Box 123, Folder 1341)
  - Teaching, Freedom of (Box 123, Folder 1342)
  - Thomas, James Augustus (Box 123, Folder 1343)
  - Toms, Clinton White (Box 123, Folder 1344)
  - Trinity College
    Includes specifications for materials and building plans for several buildings and structures on campus, including the East Campus wall; copies of Trinity College Admission Requirements, 1916-1917; correspondence; departmental records; Presidents' Reports; materials from different societies and clubs on campus; survey cards sent to alumni to determine their support for the football program; and other printed materials.
    - Administration Building Specifications (Box 123, Folder 1345)
    - Admission Requirements (Box 123, Folder 1346)
    - Alumni Association (Box 123, Folder 1347-1348)
    - Alumni Memorial Gymnasium Fund (Box 123, Folder 1349)
    - Athletics (Box 125, Folder 1350)
    - Arera Bible Lectures (Box 125, Folder 1351)
    - Bassett Affair (Box 125, Folder 1352)
    - Bell Tower Specifications (Box 125, Folder 1353)
    - Benefactors' Day (Box 125, Folder 1354)
    - Biblical Literature Dept. (Box 125, Folder 1355)
    - Biology Dept. (Box 125, Folder 1356)
    - Board of Trustees (Box 125, Folder 1357)
    - Budget (Box 125, Folder 1358)
    - Calendar, 1924 (Box 125, Folder 1359)
    - Catalog (Box 125, Folder 1360)
    - Chemistry Dept. (Box 125, Folder 1361)
    - Choir (Box 125, Folder 1362)
    - Columbian Literary Society (Box 125, Folder 1363)
    - Coordinate College for Women (Box 125, Folder 1364)
    - Debate (Box 125, Folder 1365)
    - East Dormitory Specifications (Box 125, Folder 1366)
    - Engineering Dept. (Box 125, Folder 1367)
    - English Dept. (Box 125, Folder 1368)
    - Faculty Publications, 1915-1916 (Box 125, Folder 1369)
    - Faculty Salaries (Box 125, Folder 1370)
    - Fire, 1911 (Box 125, Folder 1371)
    - Flowers Lecture (Box 125, Folder 1372)
    - Football Club Survey Cards, 1914 (Box 125, Folder 1373)
      Postcards sent to alumni to survey their opinions about whether there should be football at Trinity College.
    - Fraternities and Sororities (Box 125, Folder 1374)
    - Glee Club (Box 125, Folder 1375)
    - Greater Trinity Club (Box 125, Folder 1376)
    - Greek Dept. (Box 125, Folder 1377)
    - History Dept. (Box 125, Folder 1378)
    - Law School (Box 125, Folder 1379)
    - Libraries (Box 125, Folder 1380)
    - Methodist Summer School (Box 125, Folder 1381)
    - News Service (Box 125, Folder 1382)
    - 9019 (Box 125, Folder 1383)
    - Physics Dept. (Box 125, Folder 1384)
    - Miscellaneous Trinity College Material (Box 125, Folder 1385)
    - President's Reports, 1911-1924 (Box 126, Folder 1386)
    - President's Residence Specifications (Box 126, Folder 1387)
    - Printed Material (Box 126, Folder 1388)
    - Research Committee (Box 126, Folder 1389)
    - Reserved Officers Training Corps (Box 126, Folder 1390)
    - Sabbatical Leave (Box 126, Folder 1391)
    - Statistics (Box 126, Folder 1392)
    - Southgate Memorial Campaign (Box 126, Folder 1393)
    - Students' Army Training Corps (Box 126, Folder 1394-1395)
    - Students' Cooperative Dining Association (Box 126, Folder 1396)
    - Summer School (Box 126, Folder 1397)
    - Sunday School Extension Work (Box 126, Folder 1398)
    - Trinity Alumni Register (Box 126, Folder 1399)
    - Wall (Box 127, Folder 1400)
    - West Dormitory Specifications (Box 127, Folder 1401)
    - Women's Student Government Association (Box 127, Folder 1402)
  - Trinity Park School (Box 127, Folder 1403)
  - U.S. Federal Emergency Relief Administration (Box 127, Folder 1404)
  - U.S. National Youth Administration (Box 127, Folder 1405)
  - Vanderbilt University (Box 127, Folder 1406)
  - Watts Hospital, Durham, N.C. (Box 127, Folder 1407)
  - Wofford College, Spartanburg, S.C. (Box 127, Folder 1408)
  - Writings of Others (Box 127, Folder 1409)
    Includes synopis of Practical Idealism by James Cannon, III; synopsis of American Democracy by B. W. Ruark; synopsis of America and Evangelism by E.C. Durham; synopsis of Southern Industialism by J.R. Davis; and poem by Mary Heath Lee about the restoration of the Constitution House, 1919.
  - Clipping File (Box 127, Folder 1410-1412)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Brittle newsprint may need to be reformatted for use. Please contact University Archives staff before use.
- Bound Volumes
  Includes an arithmetic primer written by Alston W. Kendrick, Few's grandfather, 1814; a trigonometry textbook used by Few; a Bible; class records, 1913-1929 and undated, an incomplete set of Few's memoranda books for the years 1922-1933; and several alumni reviews.
  - Arithmetic Book, 1814 (Box 128, Folder 1413)
    Hand written arithmetic primer by Alston W. Kendrick, grandfather of William Preston Few.
  - Trigonometry Textbook (Box 128, Folder 1414)
    Textbook apparently used by Few during his sophomore year at Wofford College, 1886-1887.
  - Holy Bible (Box 128, Folder 1415)
    Copy apparently received by Few upon his graduation from Wofford College, June 11, 1889.
  - Class Books, 1913-1920 and undated
    Includes names of students and some grades.
    - Class Book, 1913-1915 (Box 128, Folder 1416)
    - Class Book, 1915-1918 (Box 128, Folder 1417)
    - Class Book, 1919-1920 (Box 128, Folder 1418)
    - Class Book, undated (Box 128, Folder 1419)
  - Alumni Reviews, 1923-1926 (Box 128, Folder 1420)
    Includes three copies of the Harvard Alumni Bulletin, (Oct. 4, 1923, Dec. 31, 1925, and Jan. 7, 1926) and one copy of the Williams Alumni Review, (March, 1926).
  - Memorandum Books, 1912-1933 (Box 129)
    Leather appointment books. Many dates are blank.
    - Memorandum Book, 1912 (Box 129, Folder 1421)
    - Memorandum Book, 1922 (Box 129, Folder 1422)
    - Memorandum Book, 1923 (Box 129, Folder 1423)
    - Memorandum Book, 1925 (Box 129, Folder 1424)
    - Memorandum Book, 1926 (Box 129, Folder 1425)
    - Memorandum Book, 1927 (Box 129, Folder 1426)
    - Memorandum Book, 1928 (Box 129, Folder 1427)
    - Memorandum Book, 1933 (Box 129, Folder 1428)
- Oversize Materials
  - Legal-sized Folders
    - Association of American Colleges (Box 130)
    - Duke University. Men's Student Government Association (Box 130)
    - Few, William Preston. Death of. (Box 130)
    - Methodist Board of Publication, 1923-1939 (Box 130)
    - Trinity College. Football Survey Cards, 1914. (Box 130)
  - Arithmetic Book (Box 131)
  - Diplomas (Oversize-folder 1)
    - A.B., Wofford College, Spartanburg S.C., 1889 (Oversize-folder 1)
    - Ph.D., Harvard University, 1896 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Printer's Proof with first use of term "Duke University," Durham Herald, 1924 Dec. 9 (Accompanying letter from A. A. Wilkinson, 1960 Jan. 18) (Oversize-folder 2)
- Index Cards to Few Papers
  Includes index cards apparently created by Few's office that catalog the holdings in the office files. Not all of the materials, or names, referenced on the index cards can be found in the William Preston Few Records and Papers.
  - A-E, - 1938 (Box 132)
  - F-McB, - 1938 (Box 132)
  - McC-Sti, - 1938 (Box 132)
  - Sto-Zz, - 1938 (Box 132)
  - A-K, 1939-1940 (Box 133)
  - L-Zz, 1939-1940 (Box 133)
- Additions
  - Papers, [A67-76] (Box 133)
    Includes letters, addressed to Few from William Garrott Brown, incorporated into the correspondence series.
  - Obituaries for Mrs. William Preston Few (Mary Reamey Thomas Few), [A72-68] (Box 133)
    Includes newspaper articles and editorials from the Durham Morning Herald and the Durham Sun, Jan. 8-9, 1971, incorporated into the Subject Files, Folder 1207.